<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Blog by Sulmo]]></title><description><![CDATA[서브타이틀이 어디에 작성되는가]]></description><link>https://jeoungsulmo.github.io</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 18:54:26 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[블로그 시작!]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 블로그의 시작을 알리는 글입니다. 어떤거 할지 적어볼려구여]]></description><link>https://jeoungsulmo.github.io/posts/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jeoungsulmo.github.io/posts/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 17:48:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h1 id=&quot;블로그-시작&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#%EB%B8%94%EB%A1%9C%EA%B7%B8-%EC%8B%9C%EC%9E%91&quot; aria-label=&quot;블로그 시작 permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;블로그 시작!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;어느정도 gatsby를 마무리 짓고 첫 글을 뭘로 써야 할까 하다 블로그의 전체적인 느낌이랑 주로 쓸 글들에 대해 적어볼까 합니다. 그래서 이번 글은 sulmo라는 카테고리로 하고 싶은 말을 가끔 쓰기도 하고 일기 같은 느낌도 주는카테고리로 시작합니다. &lt;del&gt;(맞습니다 잡탕입니다.)&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;블로그에서 목적으로 단순히 글을 잘 쓰고 싶은 욕구도 있고 개발 로그를 꾸준히 써보려는 목표도 있습니다. 글을 읽기 좋게 누군가에게 도움이 되게 적어보고 싶지만 그러한 준비를 끝내고 시작하려면 영영 시작 못할 거 같아서 배우는 걸 기록하자마자 최대한 바로바로 올려볼 겁니다. 이때까지 웹 개발을 주로 해왔지만 올라오는 컴파일러부터 시작할 거 같네요;; 3학년 2학기가 되니 컴파일러 같은 뭔가 고인 과목들만 개론 수업이고 나머진 다 프로젝트? 같은 느낌의 수업이다 보니..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;개발을 진짜 시작 한진 얼마 되지 않았습니다. 정말 아무것도 몰랐고 몰랐기 때문에 알기 위해 이것저것 해봤어요. 너무나도 감사하게도 피로 그래밍이라는 동아리에서 활동할 수 있었고 내가 뭘 모르는지 뭘 해야 하는지 뭐가 하고 싶은지 원하는 모든 걸 얻었습니다. 이를 시작으로 1년 좀 넘게 개발을 열심히 꾸준히 해오고 있으며 동아리 활동 이후 다음 기수의 회장이라는 무거운 자리에 반자의 반타의에의해 올랐습니다.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;처음엔 부담스러웠지만 받은 만큼 돌려준다라는 마인드로 모든 걸 부었습니다. 이때까지의 생에 몇 안 되는 정말 큰 경험이었고 개발 외적으로도 많은 것들을 얻었어요. 장문의 글과 책보단 공식 같을걸 선호했던 제가 글을 잘 쓰고 싶어 할 정도면 진짜 생각보다 크게 변한 거 같기도.. 여하튼 개발자가 되고 싶은 사람이고 이 덕분에 이 블로그에는 CS적인 부분과 가장 많이 해오던 웹 개발에서 프런트엔드 부분에 치중한 글을 많이 올려볼 예정입니다.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;이때까지 쌓여있는 노션에 정리된 글과 md파일들을 어떻게 올려야 할지 흠.. 아무튼 제가 정리한 부분들을 하나하나 쌓아가 보겠습니다. 언젠가 평범한 거물이 되어있기를 바라며 개츠비와 깃헙 페이지 감사륀…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;아 최근 장학금이랑 작은 외주한거 끌어모아 맥북사서 혼자만의 자랑아닌 자랑을 마무리로&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 960px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/d506aa979594a66e68bb8a458b9ebc6e/644c5/sulmoMac.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 48.75000000000001%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAKABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwABAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMCBf/EABYBAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIAAf/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABrUy4bYr/xAAbEAACAgMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAwARAhITM//aAAgBAQABBQJSxpyEsryuWY/1/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABH/2gAIAQMBAT8BV//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAR/9oACAECAQE/AUf/xAAaEAACAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIxEBFh/9oACAEBAAY/AltFDj3FjP/EABsQAQACAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAIRExEEGR/9oACAEBAAE/IaQZbaiBnGIk6gR2yrb3jf/aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQDD//xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAP/aAAgBAwEBPxBhX//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEA/9oACAECAQE/ECRf/8QAHRABAAMAAQUAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARITFBUWFxkf/aAAgBAQABPxBBqKx1bsu7ylR8wMTii9McePa02vVC/k//2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/d506aa979594a66e68bb8a458b9ebc6e/8ac56/sulmoMac.webp 240w,
/static/d506aa979594a66e68bb8a458b9ebc6e/d3be9/sulmoMac.webp 480w,
/static/d506aa979594a66e68bb8a458b9ebc6e/e46b2/sulmoMac.webp 960w,
/static/d506aa979594a66e68bb8a458b9ebc6e/f992d/sulmoMac.webp 1440w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/webp&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;source
          srcset=&quot;/static/d506aa979594a66e68bb8a458b9ebc6e/09b79/sulmoMac.jpg 240w,
/static/d506aa979594a66e68bb8a458b9ebc6e/7cc5e/sulmoMac.jpg 480w,
/static/d506aa979594a66e68bb8a458b9ebc6e/6a068/sulmoMac.jpg 960w,
/static/d506aa979594a66e68bb8a458b9ebc6e/644c5/sulmoMac.jpg 1440w&quot;
          sizes=&quot;(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px&quot;
          type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot;
        /&gt;
        &lt;img
          class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
          src=&quot;/static/d506aa979594a66e68bb8a458b9ebc6e/6a068/sulmoMac.jpg&quot;
          alt=&quot;sulmoMac&quot;
          title=&quot;sulmoMac&quot;
          loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
          style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        /&gt;
      &lt;/picture&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;행복..&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Humane Typography in the Digital Age]]></title><description><![CDATA[An Essay on Typography by Eric Gill takes the reader back to the year 1930. The year when a conflict between two worlds came to its term. The machines of the industrial world finally took over the handicrafts.]]></description><link>https://jeoungsulmo.github.io/posts/humane-typography-in-the-digital-age</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://jeoungsulmo.github.io/posts/humane-typography-in-the-digital-age</guid><pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2017 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-first-transition&quot;&gt;The first transition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-digital-age&quot;&gt;The digital age&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#loss-of-humanity-through-transitions&quot;&gt;Loss of humanity through transitions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chasing-perfection&quot;&gt;Chasing perfection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Essay on Typography by Eric Gill takes the reader back to the year 1930. The year when a conflict between two worlds came to its term. The machines of the industrial world finally took over the handicrafts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The typography of this industrial age was no longer handcrafted. Mass production and profit became more important. Quantity mattered more than the quality. The books and printed works in general lost a part of its humanity. The typefaces were not produced by craftsmen anymore. It was the machines printing and tying the books together now. The craftsmen had to let go of their craft and became a cog in the process. An extension of the industrial machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the victory of the industrialism didn’t mean that the craftsmen were completely extinct. The two worlds continued to coexist independently. Each recognising the good in the other — the power of industrialism and the humanity of craftsmanship. This was the second transition that would strip typography of a part of its humanity. We have to go 500 years back in time to meet the first one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-first-transition&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-first-transition&quot; aria-label=&quot;the first transition permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The first transition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar conflict emerged after the invention of the first printing press in Europe. Johannes Gutenberg invented movable type and used it to produce different compositions. His workshop could print up to 240 impressions per hour. Until then, the books were being copied by hand. All the books were handwritten and decorated with hand drawn ornaments and figures. A process of copying a book was long but each book, even a copy, was a work of art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first printed books were, at first, perceived as inferior to the handwritten ones. They were smaller and cheaper to produce. Movable type provided the printers with flexibility that allowed them to print books in languages other than Latin. Gill describes the transition to industrialism as something that people needed and wanted. Something similar happened after the first printed books emerged. People wanted books in a language they understood and they wanted books they could take with them. They were hungry for knowledge and printed books satisfied this hunger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 42–Line Bible, printed by Gutenberg.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, through this transition, the book lost a large part of its humanity. The machine took over most of the process but craftsmanship was still a part of it. The typefaces were cut manually by the first punch cutters. The paper was made by hand. The illustrations and ornaments were still being hand drawn. These were the remains of the craftsmanship that went almost extinct in the times of Eric Gill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-digital-age&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-digital-age&quot; aria-label=&quot;the digital age permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The digital age&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first transition took away a large part of humanity from written communication. Industrialisation, the second transition described by Eric Gill, took away most of what was left. But it’s the third transition that stripped it naked. Typefaces are faceless these days. They’re just fonts on our computers. Hardly anyone knows their stories. Hardly anyone cares. Flicking through thousands of typefaces and finding the “right one” is a matter of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the new computer age the proliferation of typefaces and type manipulations represents a new level of visual pollution threatening our culture. Out of thousands of typefaces, all we need are a few basic ones, and trash the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Massimo Vignelli&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typography is not about typefaces. It’s not about what looks best, it’s about what feels right. What communicates the message best. Typography, in its essence, is about the message. “Typographical design should perform optically what the speaker creates through voice and gesture of his thoughts.”, as El Lissitzky, a famous Russian typographer, put it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;loss-of-humanity-through-transitions&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#loss-of-humanity-through-transitions&quot; aria-label=&quot;loss of humanity through transitions permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Loss of humanity through transitions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each transition took away a part of humanity from written language. Handwritten books being the most humane form and the digital typefaces being the least. Overuse of Helvetica is a good example. Messages are being told in a typeface just because it’s a safe option. It’s always there. Everyone knows it but yet, nobody knows it. Stop someone on the street and ask him what Helvetica is? Ask a designer the same question. Ask him where it came from, when, why and who designed it. Most of them will fail to answer these questions. Most of them used it in their precious projects but they still don’t spot it in the street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;blockquote&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Knowledge of the quality of a typeface is of the greatest importance for the functional, aesthetic and psychological effect.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;footer&gt;
			&lt;cite&gt;— Josef Mueller-Brockmann&lt;/cite&gt;
		&lt;/footer&gt;
	&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typefaces don’t look handmade these days. And that’s all right. They don’t have to. Industrialism took that away from them and we’re fine with it. We’ve traded that part of humanity for a process that produces more books that are easier to read. That can’t be bad. And it isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humane typography will often be comparatively rough and even uncouth; but while a certain uncouthness does not seriously matter in humane works, uncouthness has no excuse whatever in the productions of the machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Eric Gill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve come close to “perfection” in the last five centuries. The letters are crisp and without rough edges. We print our compositions with high–precision printers on a high quality, machine made paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Type through 5 centuries.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We lost a part of ourselves because of this chase after perfection. We forgot about the craftsmanship along the way. And the worst part is that we don’t care. The transition to the digital age made that clear. We choose typefaces like clueless zombies. There’s no meaning in our work. Type sizes, leading, margins… It’s all just a few clicks or lines of code. The message isn’t important anymore. There’s no more “why” behind the “what”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;chasing-perfection&quot; style=&quot;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chasing-perfection&quot; aria-label=&quot;chasing perfection permalink&quot; class=&quot;anchor before&quot;&gt;&lt;svg aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot; focusable=&quot;false&quot; height=&quot;16&quot; version=&quot;1.1&quot; viewBox=&quot;0 0 16 16&quot; width=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;path fill-rule=&quot;evenodd&quot; d=&quot;M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z&quot;&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Chasing perfection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human beings aren’t perfect. Perfection is something that will always elude us. There will always be a small part of humanity in everything we do. No matter how small that part, we should make sure that it transcends the limits of the medium. We have to think about the message first. What typeface should we use and why? Does the typeface match the message and what we want to communicate with it? What will be the leading and why? Will there be more typefaces in our design? On what ground will they be combined? What makes our design unique and why? This is the part of humanity that is left in typography. It might be the last part. Are we really going to give it up?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published by &lt;a href=&quot;http://matejlatin.co.uk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Matej Latin&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/design-notes/humane-typography-in-the-digital-age-9bd5c16199bd?ref=webdesignernews.com#.lygo82z0x&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>